[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
developers are you ready it's time to
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment
collaborate build faster and deploy more
efficiently
when you can make faster decisions
there's no telling what you'll create
ready set code start coding for free
visit intersystems.com try to try iris
for software engineering radio this is
robert blumen
i'm joined today by rob skillington rob
is the cto and co-founder of
chronosphere previously
he was a technical lead on the
observability team
at uber for m3 and rob is the creator of
the open source
m3 platform rob welcome to software
engineering radio
thank you for having me robert it's uh
it's great to be here and great to get a
chance to talk
rob today we're going to be talking
about monitoring and alerting
that scale before we get into the at
scale part i'd like to do a brief
overview of monitoring and alerting
starting with
monitoring what is monitoring anyway
yeah great question you know at one
point i
uh i refer to it as keeping
computers running in a very generic term
uh but the
the more technical you know kind of term
is
really how just thinking about how
software runs
making sure that it's that it's up that
it's healthy when you're talking about a
service
and you know it kind of all the parts
of of really measuring the health and
performance of a system whether that's
you know a box product
piece of software or an online service
or
an embedded piece of hardware you know
monitoring really means the same thing
everywhere it's it's
about being able to observe that
uh and measure the the health and
performance of
of a system in question how does
alerting fit into that
yeah so alerting is uh definitely you
know been around
for quite some time nagios is a open
source
you know uh system that harks back
to a definitely more than a decade old
probably multiple decades old at this
point
and you know that that really is a it's
a great piece of software for monitoring
online services and has been for quite
some time
but that's kind of really where we came
from and
you know while it's obviously super
still used and
relevant it's it's still i guess like
the the way
that most things were done before in an
online sense which is like you
run a bit of code that probes uh a
system
and that probe returns a result and then
you kind of have this like check or fail
view of the world
uh sorry pass or fail rather in terms of
whether
a system is up or down and then you know
you kind of add more and more probes
so you can kind of prove more things
then you have this kind of partial fail
view of a lot of
independent parts of a bigger system
that helps you know you kind of
make a decision whether you think
something is healthy or not
and that i that that's uh you know
has been very popular for a very long
time um and then today you know we're
seeing a lot of
time series based monitoring going on
as well as looking at you know like
what's happening with the log output
of of your systems and kind of uh
analyzing that data but
you know fundamentally it's moving i
guess away from probe based
to really contain many other more
complicated
kind of signals coming out of these
systems as well uh such as time series
based
data and uh and log analytics branders
did that
and a probe would be we're going to
check something and either
maybe it doesn't come back at all or
comes back with a bad result that's a
fail whereas time series you could
have a more sophisticated condition that
looked at
a series of points over a five minute
window
and you might have a single bad data
point in there but that wouldn't
necessarily be a fail
right exactly it lets you look at things
more volumetrically so
you know if you were measuring the
electricity output
of you know an electrical component
that was speaking binary maybe between
zero and five volts like you
it's a lot more granular you don't just
see zero one
um you know you see exactly how how many
volts
are coming out of that component and it
and the time series is
yeah kind of like a graph of of that
signal
what happens when there's a fail so you
know
when you're talking about time series
analysis yeah there's usually
a lot of thresholds that are put in
place so it's
it's either you have some time series
that you're analyzing perhaps there's
some
summing across uh different actually
multiple compound time series to you
know present a final time series that
that you would put a a threshold on but
yeah usually it's
about declaring that the fact that you
want to make sure
a certain time series either doesn't go
below a certain value or doesn't go
above
another value and then you know when it
fails
uh or fails that precondition that that
you're trying to hold
the time series to then typically on
call
engineers who would be on call for a
system uh would get paged so that's
either
you know using something like some kind
of service like pagerduty which
which allows you to set up a roster and
then
you know when an actual event happens
that it requires investigation
you would kind of have your system tell
pagerduty about it pagerduty would find
the person on call for that roster
and then kind of page their phone by
giving them a call
or you know ping their app or send them
some kind of message
to let them know that they need to
acknowledge an incident uh needs to be
looked at and
resolved but of course you know you can
do that with with nagios pro based
checks as well you know pro fails
send a message to some system and have
that system notify a human
to go look at something the purpose of
that then is to
involve a human in the operations of the
system
to possibly fix something that won't fix
itself right
yeah a lot of the time it's uh you know
and this is actually a super
interesting topic we can talk at length
of but it's you know it's really um
this is where the the human element part
of this is
is fascinating because you know you
really want to alert on
things that actually matter you could
probably set up a million alerts
uh if you're uh you know wanted your
system to exactly uh react
and and perform in some way but really
you know it comes down to
how's your your actual system
behavior performing because that's what
you really care about you don't really
care that it you know took
an extra half a second sometimes to do
something else if that doesn't really
matter to your
to what your end system is actually
doing as a unit of work
so it's uh it's a lot about kind of
uh setting parameters on things you care
about and then
involving a human when that's necessary
you know you can use
alerts as well though for also auto
remediation or
or automation for instance like you
could set up a
in fact i know a lot of auto scaling is
done this way right like you set up an
alert
that when either cpu or some other
threshold
is exceeded you fire a web hook and then
some system that receives that web hook
will go and
perhaps scale up your cluster if it's
kind of within
a certain you know you obviously need to
put in some protection mechanisms there
you wouldn't want to infinitely scale it
up
but then you know you it allows for
automation to actually react
to uh so systems to react to to change
that that's going on in uh in the
underlying system based on signals that
your monitoring picks up on
so most of the time it's involving a
human sometimes so it's also automation
uh kind of dealing with the output of
one of those
alerts or alarms monitoring we're going
to be talking
more about concept of a metric tell us
what that is
yeah so great that's really fascinating
question i mean
um in terms of what you know day-to-day
we work with in the monitoring world a
metric
is is really a type of
event that you are uh tracking
i guess that's pretty applicable to most
other you know subcategories of
computing as well
you know it's really when i think about
what makes up a metric in the monitoring
world
it it is a schemer it's it's a type of
event that happens and it's
the different dimensions that
separate the types of events so
to give a concrete kind of example here
if we think about http requests to me
the http request returning a response
that's a metric because that's the event
that's happening you're returning
an uh an http request to an end user
and then so that's the event and then on
that metric
you have uh dimensions such as what is
the
endpoint that was served so what was the
url pattern
that the head that your handler got
called on what was the status code
so was that in the 200 range the 500
range
or the 400 range and then things like
what is the
server software that serve that request
so all those are dimensions on an
underlying
metric which is describing an event but
you know i will say that it's not always
events a lot of time as well it can be
volumetric signals so cpu usage
network through my how you know how many
megabytes or megabits per second you're
sending over
over a network and memory usage all of
those are very volumetric they're not
really events per se they're kind of
like a
point in time data point that that you
measure was the metric
this collection of dimensions and values
or is there
a single value that's the metric and
then
all these other dimensions are let's
call it metadata or labels
yeah so the way that we really like to
kind of structure it
uh in terminology is uh thinking about
you know
the metric being uh
kind of the yeah the type of thing
you're measuring so
event or or some sampling
um and then the uh combination of
dimensions makes up a time series
so for instance like going back to that
http request
example we have for instance
a single time series that is part of
an http request response is an http
request
response that was served a 200 status
code on
the slash health uh url so that's that's
one time series another time series
would be
um you know uh the same
same metric name and then the dimensions
would be 500 so internal server error
being returned from
the uh the path slash health so
time series are the underlying different
event streams
that are identified by their unique
dimension values
and then event is really the category
all of those time series
being classified as meaning you know one
thing that you're measuring or one type
of
one class of events or or component that
you're measuring if that makes sense
so we apologize to the listeners rob has
just told me it started hailing
where he is and he's moved into another
location further away from the
window so should be better for the rest
of the
podcast back to where we were
if you have these metrics and they have
dimensions which have names
how do you define in a computer system
the alert on top of these metric values
yeah so that's a great question
basically
you can think of when you're kind of
building an alert you know a lot of the
time you want to see
what the historical failure or
pass and fail rate is going to look like
so
and you can actually imagine with you
know when we're talking about those
probe based events
that's a bit harder to do this because
you don't have any signals coming out of
the system
you're literally writing code that may
pass or fail
based on what happens with the probe
whereas with time series data you know
and looking at metrics
when you create an alert you're
fundamentally
adding a threshold to basically
uh capture whether you know a an alert
would go off
or not based on signals you already have
that you can see in a graph so
typically what you do when you know you
author an alert
is you go and look at
all the different signals that are
coming out of your
system uh in a graph maybe you apply
some functions to it so
you know maybe there's some spikes that
you want to kind of
smooth out because you don't mind if you
know cpu jumps to
90 just for a short burst so you might
want to do something like average over
time
or like a moving average and then
you know so you can actually apply
transforms on top of these time series
as well
and then finally you know you kind of
put in your thresholds
for where you may want to actually alert
on that transformed uh
signal that's coming from your system so
typically what you do
you know when you're writing these
alerts is you start by
graphing and visualizing the different
metrics and underlying time series that
you're kind of
won't want to learn off of and then you
come up with a graph that makes sense to
you
logically on on the type of thing you're
trying to do so you may for instance
it's very easy to say
i don't want any internal server errors
to be returned to my users
otherwise tell me about it and so you
know a very simple
a alert would just be take the
number of times you return a internal
server error
for a given set of http endpoints and
uh whenever that exceeds you know zero
or some reasonable threshold if you know
that's something that you need to do
given the behavior of your system
and then set that threshold and then
finally depending on the monitoring
system you're doing
that you're using you may you know go to
a config file for if you're using
prometheus which is a popular open
source monitoring
tool and save that rule to the
to the config file and then either
redeploy
your system or or cause a reload to
occur
by calling an endpoint or you know if
you're using a vendor you'll probably go
to a ui
or use some command line utility to to
kind of update an alert definition
so that's typically the lifecycle we see
when you kind of author
these alerts i want to wrap up our
general discussion about monitoring and
alerting and talk more about
our main point which is at scale
so what does it mean to have monitoring
and alerting at scale what are the
challenges that start to emerge
i could see if you had a small number of
alerts
it'd be possible for one person to know
everything about it but what starts to
break when you get into larger systems
yeah good question so the main thing you
know at at scale that tends to happen is
your system gets more complex you know
whether that's uh
your your product getting more complex
or uh
fundamentally you're scaling out the
team
and uh you know the team
to support some product line needs to
refactor the code in such a way that
that is more complex but typically you
know one of the two
are happening and uh you have
uh just a lot more code paths now
to track so in regards to
kind of monitoring that you need to
think about
all the different things um that can go
wrong i would start with really though
just defining what your slas are you
know what what are your service level
agreements what
what is the things that when you break a
contract
uh you will get a
uh customer or user or
or your manager upset what will upset
them essentially
uh what are those contracts look like
and then essentially putting alerts
on those and then you know in a more
complex system
uh what tends to happen is that you know
you have the layer
that interacts with the end user but
then you have layers below as well so
you'll have like
uh a data layer and that data layer may
have a contract with
other developers inside the company that
it should return
reasonably within 50 milliseconds or
something like that
a record about a user or a record about
some
some object and so you really think of
it like
laying down your monitoring in terms of
layering on
the layers of an onion and so uh you
know
at the the most core layer you you do
want some alerts as well and and at the
medium and then
you know at the the most important are
the slas and the contracts you have that
you actually have at the the very edge
of your system
but you want to know ahead of time when
uh things closer to the lower level
start to misbehave because that can
cause a cascading failure and
kind of impact all of your your product
or you know or system at that at the
higher layers so
typically what tends to happen when you
scale out is
you need to cover more http endpoints
you need to cover
more uh server versions that you're
tracking are in production
you probably have more either in
vm instances or machines or containers
running your software so you have
many more points of failure and you know
you want to basically make sure that
when you do get an alert that goes off
you can drill down
exactly to which one of those points was
a failure
and so fundamentally you're just adding
dimensions to a lot of these metrics
whether it's
because you have a more complex product
or because your infrastructure is more
complex
and then uh it really comes down to
you know how do you deal with that level
of complexity and scale of the
the monitoring data and do you do that
in a way that's sane or does it become
unmanageable and it's just a mess of
alerts and uh
and no one really can understand what's
going on because
you know you're not doing it in a clean
consistent manner across your
system so that's some of the things to
really think about and
some of the common things that become
problems
very quickly and uh you know if your
tools are working against you
and you you can't just kind of collect
more monitoring data and you can't
you know if that's problematic or or
cost ineffective because it's too
expensive
um or perhaps you know the
there's just frictions there that is
that is hard to use maybe your query
language for creating these time series
is super obtuse
and not well documented which is why we
love you know open source
software in this space you know i'm an
open metrics contributor
which is a standard here in this space
and
you know i think that uh you really want
your tools to work with you
and you want there to be some knowledge
and nomenclature that's common to what
you're doing amongst the team
and you know that that depending on the
tool you're using
whether that's some very niche specific
vendor tool or
some very common popular open source
tool or
or a mix of the two you know you really
want to think about that as well
as you start to scale up your monitoring
needs
you know a number of points there some
of the main
takeaways for me is as a system
scales up you simply have more metrics
because there are more things to monitor
on and more things
to alert on and then you have a lot more
data which is going to
create load on the monitoring tools and
if you have a database in your
monitoring system
you mentioned that this manifests as
more dimensions
and and what i think you're talking
about is let's say that all your
services are http
and if the service which originated the
metric if that is a dimension then
that manifests as more values in the
given dimension
did i get that right right yeah and and
especially if you're
you know uh playing in a kubernetes
world or
some kind of container system it's not
even just a service it's a service and
then the underlying
uh process id because of course you know
if you run
200 instances of a single service and on
really small containers
when something goes wrong if it's hyper
localized to just one of them
you kind of need that dimension of which
container was running it
uh to be able to to localize the problem
and
kind of uh quickly go from an alert to
debugging your application we're veering
into this topic which i wanted to cover
the idea in monitoring of high
cardinality and high dimension
monitoring
which is something you you told me that
you wanted to talk about
i'll let you talk about that now what
what do you mean by that
and how does that relate to scale
yeah great question um and and thank you
for yeah let me kind of
kind of bring it up i mean a little bit
to what i was kind of talking about
previously with with what happens you
know as you start to scale up
uh a complex system or a engineering
team that's working on
on a system that that starts to accrue a
lot of
complexity in it what typically
you know tends to happen is it it starts
to look like a
bowl of spaghetti from the outside um if
you don't
if you can't really see what's going on
and
uh you know a lot of people start with
like reading the code uh right
but at a certain level and even with
three or four engineers
or developers you know you you can
reach a point where that's just
inefficient essentially and honestly
you know when you're encountering a
failure in a system
the last thing you want to do is go read
the code you want to mitigate the
problem first right
and uh logs is typically
you know being very useful here but with
the
you know kind of change which is
happening out there
that's seeing a lot more things run on
the thermal
environments uh in the cloud and you
know more people are using
lots and lots of containers instead of a
few vms
and and people are also using
distributed systems more frequently
where they would have had just one
monolithic
system microservices are becoming more
popular i think
you have to be really careful with how
far you go in in that direction
and i have stories on that but it
technically you know really what i'm
the kind of trend that i'm talking about
here though is that
uh essentially you really need
some direction at a higher level than
just thinking like i have a problem
i need to go look at the logs or read
the code like that's
it's kind of already it just takes so
long
to perform that analysis that you know
when you're trying to mitigate a problem
or understand even just how a larger
system is working at a higher level
you really need a lot of signals coming
out of that system that
that makes sense to you and make sense
to others without having to
to go and deep dive on a specific set of
logs or
or try to understand how a code this a
flow
you know a code path is working based on
the code so
high dimensionality metrics is really
about giving you those signals at
at higher and higher levels granularity
so that when you do trigger
an alert it's it's not just telling you
that you know
you've got a spike in error rate it's
telling you you've got a spike in error
rate
there's a specific http endpoint that's
exhibiting the problem
and it only happens with the new version
of the code you rolled out
and only with clients that is
you know if we talk about an example
where you're using a mobile application
and serving traffic to a mobile
application
it's only you know you're only seeing an
error right error rate
with the new code with a mobile client
of a specific version or operating
system
so all those extra caveats there
helps you get to your root cause much
faster
but having those extra dimensions and
those extra signals that gives you depth
into the problem
or or how you know this the system is
just behaving in general is super uh
helpful and that
and that's that's really what we when
you keep adding those dimensions that's
what causes high cardinality because
high cardinality is
really talking about the number of
unique time series it's not talking
about the metrics
you might still be tracking the same
type of things but you
the number of underlying time series
explodes because
you want to slice and dice on a high
number of dimensions
hiring a software engineer then we
recommend working with g2i
g2i is the most effective way to
discover talented and pre-vetted
engineers for every project
g2i vets their talent pool through
technical interviews and various code
challenges which are graded by actual
engineers
saving you time and guaranteeing you top
quality through their transparent
grading
they specialize in react react native
and no
js interested in learning more
then go to g2i.co
if i averaged everything together
it might look fine but what you're
saying is if i was able to see
this given metric of latency and group
it based on
user agent e the end point it's hitting
whether it's a mobile or fixed
code version and let's add three more
things and you might see that out of
that
big high dimension space that one of
them
is behaving very badly and that set of
users is having a terrible experience
which i would not see if i averaged it
all together right
exactly and you know a concrete example
here is you know at uber
we would have these type of things where
uh certain telecom providers would go
dark
with the routing to our back end and
sometimes it was the routing to our back
end and not all
internet or all internet websites so
it's
like you know if you're on 18t and
you're in
some some part of the us that's
experiencing a routing
issue to a a network server
that's that was hosting uber um you may
be impacted
and that's a terrible user experience
like if we don't want you know
especially at the company we wouldn't
want specific
both users of the system to experience a
hyper
outage like that for potentially days at
a time we need to know about that you
know
and and when you just have user reports
from the wild it's really hard to
correlate that so
even just by adding a dimension of what
telecom provider
it looked like an ip address was coming
from as well as like
uh you know certain things around where
the
the mobile client was pinging in from
that helped
a lot to try and you know get to a root
cause much quicker and understand
a root cause and then you know when you
think about like netflix
they talk um about this problem as well
where they're they know they can know
they can tell
that a specific ios version in
brazil watching a certain title is not
able to play back a
a mp4 you know file that they've encoded
slightly differently to all the rest so
that level of diagnostics is is
kind of required in a in this world
that's growing like more complex and
and also just honestly you know makes
for a lot easier to actually see what's
happening yeah and
in that when you were talking about
averaging everything
out like if you just looked at how many
playback failures happened for that one
tv show on netflix you might not see the
fact that this one specific
ios version in brazil is experiencing a
hyper local problem
it might just look like oh well less
than
one or two percent who cares uh
and and um but that's really actually an
underlying problem that can be fixed if
you know what the root
cause is and you can kind of drill down
quickly i think
now you haven't said this but i am
inferring this from what you said so the
cardinality is the number of different
values
you can have on a metric and then the
dimension is the size of the overall
space when you multiply all these
cardinalities
together did i extract that correctly
from what you said
yeah i would really probably think about
it just as
metric made up of many time series
influenced by the dimensions so like
multiplying the unique dimension values
together gives you number of time series
for a metric
and then the cardinality is really just
the number of unique time series that
that's really the same thing so it's
it's uh that's how i like to think about
it okay
and we're going to be talking about high
cardinality
could you give us some numbers or orders
of magnitude in a
organization like an uber or a netflix
what are we looking at here for how many
unique time
series how many distinct values are
there i could guess for countries you
could have dozens or a hundred
give us some concrete numbers yeah yeah
definitely
yeah i'd love to do that uh yeah if we
look at
even like go back to our http example
you know we have
um five status codes
perhaps like hp 200 400 500
300 and maybe even or none of those
and then uh so those are categories
they're not even status codes you might
have like 20 status codes
but let's just talk about five for now
because that's probably five that are
important to you
um and then say you're monitoring a
hundred endpoints
and then say your monitor like
maybe your product uh or or system
behaves differently depending on which
country the user is in so
that's maybe say you operate in a
hundred different countries
and then you think about like server
version so
you may have probably 10 it depends on
your system but maybe you've got 10
different versions of your
of your server version rolled out
depending on you know a canary or a
staging environment or
or a different region that you're
operating maybe you're serving traffic
out of different cloud regions
so so that's kind of like status code
five
buy endpoints 100 say and then buy
another 100
for the cities um and then say you run
in six regions so that's
and i've always relied on the calculator
so don't mind me while i multiply
live the the number here you know so
we're talking that's already a very
large number
yeah we're talking about 300 000 time
series there so that's six regions
five different status codes 100
endpoints and oh sorry we're talking
about
30 000 i i put in 10 100 for different
server versions but 10 server versions
is much more realistic
so that's 30 000 time series you can
imagine if you have if you want to
monitor on anything else like
uh user client agent like whether it's
chrome
or safari or whether it's ios or android
on mobile
that's that's going to multiply that 30
000 again
so you very quickly get to these
hundreds of thousands um
millions now granted that is a pretty
high cardinality
metric but you kind of you know in these
worlds we we exist in especially when
you add container label to that
you might operate over 200 containers
and those container
containers might rotate as well so if
you're looking back over time
you know you've got if you deployed your
200 containers twice
now there's 400 different containers
that you could possibly be looking at
the results from over over a time window
that you look at
so yeah these numbers multiply very
quickly even for small companies
netflix you know at monodrama uh which
is a monitoring conference held in
portland oregon
you know they they mentioned that their
system had three billion
unique time series in it and
and that was kind of level cardinality
they were working with
you know at uber there were there were
tons of experimentation going on so we
had tons of dimensions
you know surge algorithms fluctuated
dynamically and that
that kind of depended on which region
you're in so
we actually had 11 billion time series
before you know i left the company to
start
chronosphere and it's it's an extreme
challenge
i think when you're when you real like
the app software developers
become addicted to this stuff as well
like at uber uh we had
more than half of the engineering team
daily
daily visit with unique sessions uh
are our monitoring tool m3 and
interacting with the graphs
or setting up alerts or checking on on
an experiment that we're they were
running
so you know our internal google
analytics showed it was
probably the most popular tool and most
visited next to our deployment system at
the company
i can see how having this high
dimensionality would enable you to
service problems it might be obscured
if you average things together but do
you have the
reverse problem if something was
affecting all user agents
in six countries across five code
versions
you don't want to get i can't do that
number in my head but you don't want to
get
600 alerts when there is
one problem do you have a way of
grouping together
so that you can collapse dimensions when
it makes sense to do that
most definitely that that is a common
problem that you know you've identified
there
that is is hard to get right i will say
like it depends on the tool you're using
but
a lot of tools can do this really wrong
and you will get
you will get your phone blowing up so
the
typical way that you know the prometheus
which is
a popular open source monitoring and
learning tool does this
is an m3 is is really you know a
scalable long-term
storage and back end for for prometheus
metrics
but the typical way in a prometheus
world you would do this
is uh you set up your notification
um mechanism the endpoints you want to
be notified on
so one would be like pagerduty and then
you essentially
say that you want to group things by
always by alert name so you author an
alert
and you unless you if you don't group by
an alert name then you only get a signal
yes or no whether it's going off
so first you want to group by alert name
so you get an alert for each type of
alert
and then and then you basically make
sure that you know 600 cities
are being affected or 100 endpoints
you're only going to get one alert for
that and so it'll group by
everything else will get automatically
grouped by but then
essentially you will want to retain that
underlying
cardinality data on the metrics so that
when you see the alert
it can show you all the different
combinations of of the dimensions that
are
are currently exceeding the thresholds
that you've set
and uh that helps weather the storm
very quickly but there's there's plenty
of tools out there that don't do that
and and you will see an explosion like
you're talking about
and then you know you could go even
further if you do want to get that
broken down that alert broken down
by different regions uh you can do that
as well and route the different regions
to different
people so maybe there are different
people on call for different uh things
based on one of the dimensions of of the
metric that you're monitoring
where i want to get to in the time we
have left is
rob you've done a great job so far at
setting up
the the problem and what i want to get
to in the time we have left
a little bit about how you solve it in
the monitoring
platform so let's briefly just spend
a few minutes outlining either you could
pick prometheus
or a generic monitoring tool that
combines
features of the common products so what
does a monitoring tool look like
and then we're going to ask how do you
solve this problem of having
uh six million alerts without
spending a um excessive amount of cost
on it let's talk about what does a
monitoring system
architecture look like yeah
that's a great question and yeah i think
you know the general conception of of
how to do this
uh is is in flux like we
we're live in the software development
world um
it's not like civil engineering there's
not a uh
you know a really well oiled set of
processes to do this
i will say there's obviously you know a
lot of well-defined ways to do it but
it's
it's it is changing more than in an
industry like civil engineering where
you build something in a given way and
you know that build
that bridge is going to stay up with
monitoring
it is you know one of the more popular
ways of doing it especially in open
source today
is using something like prometheus which
will
you know collect signals from your
applications you develop as well as
it'll collect signals from
the machines that your applications run
on so to get cpu memory and
network signals uh from it and those
you know so and honestly most generic
monitoring systems will do this as well
this is how they do it kind of differ
and then essentially you know once you
have that stream of information
going from your application as well as
your infrastructure to a single place
that's when you run into the problem of
okay well now how do i actually
add capacity to the signals that i'm
collecting
and just before we dive into that you
know that one of the first things you
want to solve though is
how do you lower the friction for you to
add a signal
to the system that you set up so you
want to use client libraries
uh that are popular that are used by
many people
and you know have some
some kind of backing that they and
maturity to them
um so the prometheus client library for
instance works in
every language under the sun prometheus
also has this concept of exporters
so if you want to monitor a system that
you don't own there's likely an
exporter for that so you know there's
things like an nginx
import exporter uh redis exporter on my
sql exporter things like that
so you want to work out all your touch
points and how to get signals into the
system
lower that friction as much as possible
whether you're using a vendor or
yeah something like prometheus and open
source and then once they're all
uh kind of being collected in one place
you need to be able to use
a system that can scale out and so you
know depending on
what type of organization uh you you're
currently you know uh working for
or what kind of system you're developing
you'll
you'll have different needs right so if
you if you never
expand from if your if your system never
gets complex enough
to exceed you know a million or a
million time series or so
or or even fewer or even uh you know a
little bit more than that
one single prometheus server is going to
be absolutely fine for you
but we you know we just did that maths
on that http example and we got to 30
000 very quickly
so you could imagine actually exceeding
a few million pretty quickly
um and you know prometheus has certain
ways where you can continue to use
prometheus even once you've exceeded a
single service capacity
you you kind of separate out what you're
monitoring they go to separate
prometheus instances and then when
you're looking at graphs you kind of
like select which prometheus server you
want to get your results back from
but then you know you may also just want
to centralize all of this
because that's kind of talking about
separating out
the the metrics to be collected by
different things and then
kind of gluing systems on top to look at
them
um and switching between them but
there's a lot of popular things in open
source
that that help you actually uh send uh
metrics to a central place either most
most of the time through prometheus if
you're
in the prometheus ecosystem so you kind
of deploy these prometheus servers
and separate what they're gonna monitor
and then they all
send prometheus will send data to a
central
uh long-term storage or a central
monitoring backend
and that's where you know m3 which is an
open source project that that
i the open source part of it i kind of
worked on at uber and
and that's been uh you know available in
open source 2018
that's that's a one of those central
back ends uh there's also thanos
which is another open source project in
this space
and you know that one that thanos
project will back up its metrics to
to s3 or some other kind of object store
in the cloud
whereas like m3 is more of an actual
database so you know you you
it it'll look like a database and give
you access to
to metrics that it has on disk so you
know depending on your needs you may
lean to one
centralized backend versus another and
uh you know i
really think of these as gating
functions right like when you're getting
started
prometheus works great out of the out of
the box
um you know when you're eclipsing one
prometheus server you can still extend
it a little bit further with just a few
little tricks and then when you go up
even higher than that
and lots of you've got developers that
are that are kind of scaling and you
don't want
any one team to have to manage their own
monitoring infrastructure
you would look at something like thanos
if if you're you know want something
that to get you started um and just kind
of historically back up the metrics and
and have access to them maybe at higher
latency and all that but but still there
with it but with having the metrics in
an object store or you look at something
like m3
if you want super high reliability by
replicating the monitoring data
um across availability zones in the
cloud region
so you know at uber that was that was
really important to us
uh an hour of gap of monitoring it could
have meant
we you know i that could have been such
a brand impacting event
that we may as well have packed up our
bags and gone home
right so you know it really depends
about like
what kind of playing field you're
currently playing in and what makes
sense to you
depending on on on what you're doing to
which tool you reach for and what vendor
you reach for
some vendors are you know more expensive
and
easy to use others are cost effective
focus on scale and then other some are
have proprietary lock-in languages
others
you know um will be more prometheus and
open-source friendly
and use industry standards so that's
kind of the things that go on in my head
when i'm talk
when you think about how to like really
think about this and dissect what your
needs are
depending on what you're doing all right
so to recap that you have
something which is in compiled in or
very close to the stuff you're
monitoring that can pull the metrics out
and then you need to
transit them somewhere to uh central
back and then you store at least a
certain amount of data in some kind of
persistent store that keeps
values either as long
as you want or for as long as you can
afford because it could be
quite a lot of data that be the main
architectural highlights
yeah i think that's that's really what
you um need to start off with is
is uh what what's going to be
frictionless free to use
and yeah and which central back end do
you want to
to kind of store it in and what are your
requirements and
and kind of you know budget as well for
for that i want to get into the the
programming or engineering problem of
we talked earlier about you define
alerts alert is
some code which operates on a time
series and it produces a value which
might be
pass fail or it might be a value
compared to a threshold
and then that's pass valve that
determines whether the alert fires or
not
then we were talking about this
cardinality where you've got a big high
dimension
space in that if any one single cell in
this big high dimension matrix
is going into a fail state you need to
generate an alert so now
from uh software engineering standpoint
how how do you code that up and how much
memory and computation does it take to
have 30 000
time series that you're simultaneously
evaluating against
this stream of 30 000 different
uh incoming metrics streams yeah i mean
that's a great question it's
it can vary a lot different different
monitoring workloads
even with the same level of cardinality
can be very different depending on like
the
time series functions you're playing on
them so for instance you know if you
want to do a time
series query that sums all uh
internal server errors up by by city
that resulting uh matrix output is
you know only the amount of cities you
run in so that's a
you know a lower number of time series
but if you want to
then sum them up not and group by not
just by city but you want to
then group them up by ios or
ios or android version or something else
then that's a even higher resulting
matrix output so you know just to lay
down some
some basic numbers to get an idea if
you're
kind of collecting 10 000 time
series per second which to be fair if
you're only going to
actually take a point in time sample
every 30 seconds
you're probably even with like a
cardinality of thirty thousand you're
not it's not gonna be ten thousand per
second
right it's going to be a thousand per
second so
if you're talking about ten thousand per
second
various open source back ends here
depending on what you're using
we'll we'll use 10 to 20 gigabytes of
memory
perhaps and uh depending on how many
queries you throw at it so how many
you know time series queries you're
throwing at it it could probably
easily handle like maybe 50 to 100
alerts uh and you're talking about maybe
four or five cores so you probably want
like an eight core machine for that
but that's that's really you know
talking about it from a prometheus
point of view m3 is you know similar
levels of
scalability and resource usage these are
highly advanced systems though you know
back in the day
10 000 per second with that type of
hardware
not possible um you know there's a lot
that's gone into that there's
there was tia said the tsa compression
algorithm that came out of facebook
that allowed for 11x compression on
float data you know that's talking about
turning a 16 byte
timestamp value of two eight eight byte
numbers into roughly it averages out
using this algorithm to 1.4 bytes per
data point
so that compression ratio allows you to
store way more memory
and you know if you're frequently
evaluating this so they're being pulled
into memory a lot so
reducing you know that memory usage is
only possible with algorithms like tia
said
and then you've also just got much more
sophisticated storage engines now
which um you know are smart and
optimized for the right thing you know
you don't need acid transactions and
monitoring uh
you you uh you just have high volume and
so like kind of
fully understanding that and refining
and refining the system
to to kind of hyper optimize for that
type of data structure and that type of
collection
um has enabled us to to really be able
to do
you know uh to kind of like get to those
sorts of numbers
and you know a single m3 database node
can do
hundreds of thousands and you know
sometimes millions of data points per
second but we're talking about
pretty large machines um when we're
talking about those kind of numbers so
you know two hundreds of gigabytes of
ram and 16 to 32 cores that kind of
thing
i think this problem would naturally
incline toward
some degree of sharding in that if
you're say monitoring different
regions you might even have different
groups of people who respond
in north america europe and asia
and you could have entirely different
monitoring back-ends even though they're
monitoring
different segments of the same metric
right yeah no definitely it's uh it's
it's definitely a
thing that leans very it
it natively can be partitioned and
uh you know i think that
distributed systems in its very key is
is about kind of partitioning and how do
you
you know map and reduce to query this
type of data and
and how do you even fairly distribute
the workload like you don't want some
servers working much harder than others
because then you've got a micro
management problem
you know an m3 under under the hood
actually we'll do a
you know use a fairly good hash function
to work out whether
the combination dimensions you're
storing and which server it should be
stored on
and that helps us actually get you know
like when we talk about a server that a
cluster that's doing 300
000 rights if you have three nodes it
it'll very evenly be doing about 100 000
each per
per second so you know there's a lot
that goes into making sure that
these systems can scale out horizontally
in a way that's
sane without you having to micromanage
the storage aspects to it
prometheus does tend to be single node
as i kind of mentioned it's a bit of a
more decentralized
storage model but it is uh which you can
partition yourself and
it is fascinating though how to how to
operate these things
you mentioned the open source m3 which
you're involved in and i covered that in
your
biography without saying exactly what it
is give us a proper introduction to
m3 yeah uh no i can definitely speak
more to that
so so m3 is really a
a metrics platform and its core and you
know
it's primarily a prometheus long-term
storage backend and what i mean by that
is so
when we talked about you know what do
you choose as your
your monitoring back end um these days
it's not just talking about a single
monitoring back and it may
you may use different tools in your
monitoring pipeline
to pipe your data one or
two or n places but you know with
prometheus and m3
they kind of plug together nicely to
to give you basically a a single scale
out back end for
the underlying data so you can point all
your alerts and your dashboards to m3
but use prometheus you know to kind of
do the front line uh collection of
metrics
before sending them to a central place
and that that kind of
so m3 is really adding a layer to either
an existing metric system or
if you're using stats to your graphite
which m3 also supports it it can
ingest that type of metrics data
directly
and so m3 is really a what we like to
think of as a central
monitoring both database as well as
aggregators so m3 actually contains
unlike many other monitoring systems
and an optional layer of aggregation you
can perform on the signals that come
into the system
and this was extremely um helpful at
uber
so you know some of these super high
cardinality use cases we're talking
about
we actually didn't care about the
container
uh sometimes um the container labels so
the ab
the single container you know if we're
actually monitoring on telecom provider
we don't really care
that the telecom provider the telecom
provider will be down for all the
containers
and um if the telecom is experiencing an
outage
so we would actually transform these
metrics as they came in to the metrics
platform in that central back end that
m3 is
and so when we think about m3 it's
really a time series database that's
horizontally scalable
at the bottom it's optionally an
aggregation
a streaming metrics aggregator which can
do transform on
metrics that are coming in on the way in
if you want to which will help with even
you know a higher level of scale you
know is really for advanced users
and then it's the uh the query service
uh of course that sits on top that
allows you to apply all these transforms
and you can kind of actually run all of
these in one single process as you get
started with m3
and then separate the roles out if you
want to isolate
the ingestion of metrics and the
querying of metrics so that
you know one huge query doesn't
interrupt your incoming steady stream of
metrics
things like that so it's it's really a
scale out
multi-component uh metrics platform that
you can either start getting
you know getting started with just a
single node but then spin
spin out the different components
separately and and it was the the center
and the core of of monitoring at uber
and it's also
the center in the core of the uh the
monitoring and observability
hosted service that we provided
chronosphere
rob we're getting near end of time
before we wrap up
would you like to share with listeners
where they can find you or point them to
any resources
on the internet yeah of course um yeah i
would love uh
if anyone's interested more on this
topic i share my thoughts frequently on
it uh on my
twitter handle that's twitter.com
forward slash rosekili so
r-o-s-k-i-l-l-i
all these will be in the show notes
right and then you know
just visit uh if you're interested in m3
at all you can visit
m3db.io and you know the chronosphere
which is a hosted platform on m3 is at
chronosphere.io and you can find more
about it there
rob skilling thank you for speaking to
software engineering radio
this has been robert blumen it's been
fantastic robert thank you so much
thank you developers take your marks
it's time to upgrade your data platform
to inner systems iris
it's time to deliver complex mission
critical applications in the fastest
route possible
it's time to use any data from any
source it's time to embed
analytics and create interactive user
interfaces so what are you waiting for
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment
collaborate build faster and deploy more
efficiently
done and done tomorrow's next
breakthroughs are waiting for you today
intersystems iris data platform the
fastest way to build applications
ready set code
start coding for free visit
intersystems.com
try to try iris
[Music]
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening
you